Finding Aid for the Kenneth Macgowan Papers LSC.0887
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kenneth Macgowan papers
1915-1970
UCLA Library Special Collections
Macgowan, Kenneth
LSC.0887
44 Linear Feet (88 boxes)
3 oversize_boxes
Kenneth Macgowan (1888-1963) was a drama critic for newspapers and magazines, a publicity director, producer and director with the Actor's Theater (1927-29), and the first department chair at the UCLA Theater Arts Department (1946-58). He was also interested in the anthropological field of archaeology. His publications include The theater of tomorrow (1921), Footlights across America (1929), Early man in the new world (1950), and Behind the screen: the history and technique of the motion picture (1965). The collection consists of materials related to Macgowan's careers in theater, motion pictures, and academia as well as material related to his interest in anthropology.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Kenneth Macgowan, 1965-71.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9922210983606533>
Biography
Macgowan was born in Winthrop, Massachusetts, November 30, 1888; graduated Harvard, 1911; married Edna Behre, 1913; drama critic for Philadelphia evening ledger, the New York globe, Vogue, Theatre arts magazine, and Shadowland; publicity director for Goldwyn Pictures Corporation, 1918-19; formed an association with Eugene O'Neill and Robert Edmond Jones at the Provincetown Playhouse; producer and director with the Actor's Theater, 1927-29; worked at RKO Studios (early 1930s-35), 20th Century Fox (1935-41), and Paramount Studios (1944-46); among his many film credits is La Cucaracha, the first production in modern Technicolor; instructor and first department chair at the UCLA Theater Arts Department (1946-58); studied both anthropology and archaeology; publications include The theater of tomorrow (1921), Footlights across America (1929), Early man in the new world (1950), Behind the screen: the history and technique of the motion picture (1965); he died of cancer on August 27, 1963.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials related to Macgowan's careers in theater, motion pictures, and academia. Also includes material related to Macgowan's interest in anthropology and archaeology. Correspondents include Robert Edmond Jones and Lee Simonson. Includes items related to Eugene O'Neill and the Provincetown Playhouse.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Special projects (Boxes 1-12).
Manuscripts (Boxes 13-22).
Involvement with little theaters, ca. 1920-30 (Boxes 23-27).
Motion picture production files (Boxes 28-39).
Clippings from newspapers and periodicals, ephemera and other material (Boxes 37-53).
Activities as an educator (Boxes 54-74).
Additional material, June 1966 (Boxes 75-88).
Items Removed from Collection
Drawing, De Emp'rer's Palace, by Cleon Throckmorton catalogued separately in the Original Works of Art on Paper (Collection 99). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Theater critics -- Archives.; Theatrical producers and directors -- Archives.; Motion picture producers and directors -- Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Theater Arts--Faculty -- Archives; Macgowan, Kenneth -- Archives
- Special Projects
  - Anthropology
    - Anthropology - Correspondence Pertaining to Anthropological Concerns and Projects
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re anthropological matters. v.p., 1938-1958.; 95 items. Holograph and typescript (some carbon). (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Scope and Contents note
        Included are copies of letters and replies from Mr. Macgowan to correspondents. All items are arranged alphabetically.
        General note
        Correspondents include:
        - The American Museum of Natural History., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Byers, Douglas S., 8 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Campbell, Elizabeth W. Crózer Mrs. William H. Campbell., 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - The Carnegie institution of Washington. Office of publications., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Caso, Alfanso., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Childs, Eversly., 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Dow, Sterling., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Foster, Norman., 6 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Gamio, Manuel., 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Gillmor, Frances., 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Gross, Hugo., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Harrington, M.R., 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Harris, Walter A., 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - The Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Makemson, Maud W., 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Marquina, Ignacio., 10 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Merrill, Robert H., 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - National Geographic Magazine. Washington, D.C., 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Noguera, E., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Prehistoric society. Cambridge, England., 10 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Rainey, Froelich., 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Roberts, Frank H.H. Jr., 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Ruettinger, John W., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - The San Diego museum., 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Strong, William Duncan., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Tozzer, Alfred M., 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Carbon copies of letters from Kenneth Macgowan to various persons re anthropological matters, with no return correspondence included, plus a few announcements. v.p., v.d.; 11 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and the American Film Center, re anthropological matters. v.p., 1938-1940.; 88 items. Typescript (some carbon). (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and Harold S. Gladwin, re anthropological matters. v.p., 1934-1942.; 62 items. Holograph and typescript (some carbon). (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Continued in next folder.
      - Correspondence with Harold S. Gladwin re anthropological matters, continued. v.p., 1943-1947.; 85 items. Holograph and typescript (some carbon). (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence re the Latin American Film Project, with which Kenneth Macgowan was involved. [New York], 1941-1942.; 7 items. Typescript (much carbon). (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Also included are records and other related material.
        Included is one letter from George Vaillant.
        Items are arranged chronologically.
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and the Middle American Research Institute re anthropological matters. v.p., 1939-1940.; 14 items. Typescript (much carbon). (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and The University Museum of the University of Pennsylvania re anthropological matters. v.p., 1939-1960.; 24 items. Holograph and typescript (some carbon). (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re the Pre-Columbian Fund. v.p., 1944-1947.; 31 items. Holograph and typescript (some carbon). (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Arizona State Museum, University of Arizona., 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Carnegie corporation of New York., 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Chicago. The University of Chicago. Department of anthropology., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Ekholm, Gordon., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Kelly, Isabel., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Kroeber, A.L., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Rockefeller, Nelson A., 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - The society for American archaeology., 7 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - The southwest museum. Los Angeles., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Sproul, Robert G., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Strong, William Duncan., 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Pre-Columbian Fund. Material re the project. v.p., 1945.; 29 items. Typescript (mostly carbon and some mimeograph). (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Including a proposal for the fund, and quotations from letters of acceptance.
      - Pre-Columbian Fund. n.p., 1945.; 39 items. Typescript (mostly carbon, and some mimeograph) and printed. (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Material re the project, including articles about it, both printed and typescript, mailing lists, and the Constitution for the project.
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re Tule Springs Project, a National Science Foundation project. v.p., 1962.; 9 items. Typescript (some carbon). Also included are related materials. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and T.A. Willard re anthropological matters. Beverly Hills, California, 1939-1940.; 7 items. Typescript (some carbon). (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Anthropology - Correspondence, Manuscripts and Ephemera
      Including Material re Gabriel S. Yorke's Translation of Sahagun.
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re the translation into English of the History of Ancient Mexico,, by Sahagun (Fray Bernardino de). v.p., v.d., 1547-1577; 42 items. Typescript (some carbon). (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - The Arthur G. Clark Company, publishers and booksellers., 7 items. (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - The coordinator of inter-American affairs., 15 items. (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Fisk University. Department of social sciences., 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Hewett, Edgar L., 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Kelly, Isabel., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - MacLeish, Archibald., 8 items. (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Smisor, George T., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Copies of letters from Kenneth Macgowan to various persons re translation of Sahagun, for which no replies were included. n.p., 1944, 1946.; 3 items. Typescript (carbon). (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - The English translation of the History of Mexico, 1547-1577, by Sahagun (Fray Bernardino de). [Beverly Hills, California?], 1943.; 116 leaves. Typescript (mostly carbon) with some corrections and notations. (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Apparently, this is not a completed version, nor are the leaves in any exact order.
        Also included, here, are three letters from Gabriel Yorke to Kenneth Macgowan re translation.
        Additional leaves, mostly in numerical order, are filed in subsequent folders.
      - The English translation of the History of Mexico, 1547-1577, by Sahagun... continued. [Beverly Hills, California?], 1943.; 107 leaves. Typescript (mostly carbon). (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - The English translation of the History of Mexico, 1547-1577, by Sahagun... continued. [Beverly Hills, California?], 1943.; 107 leaves. Typescript (mostly carbon). (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - [Gabriel S. Yorke, obituary]. [California], n.d.; 4 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Also included is a newspaper clipping, the printed version of the obituary. [California] n.d.
      - Ephemera. Miscellaneous booklets, pamphlets and other published material re anthropology. v.p., v.d.; 7 items. Printed. (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Includes reprints of articles.
      - The International Directory of Anthropologists, edited by Melville J. Herskovits. Washington, D.C.,, third edition., 1950; 1 item. Paperbound. (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Book lists and announcements of publication of various works primarily on subjects re anthropology, and miscellaneous material. v.p., v.d.; 13 items. Printed. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Book catalogs from various dealers, particularly referring to works on subjects re anthropology. Amsterdam, Holland; and Lima, Peru, v.d.; 5 items. Mimeograph. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Anthropology - Manuscripts and Ephemera, Articles, Reviews, and Clippings
      - Articles and reviews re anthropology. v.p., v.d.; 54 leaves. Typescript (almost all carbon). (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Included also, are a few newspaper clippings of the articles in print.
        Each item is grouped separately and labeled within the folder.
        The articles include:
        - [Architectural momuments and stone sculptures in Mexico and Guatemala] California, October 1940.; 13 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 3, Folder 1)
          2 versions.
        - Back to the brute. California, 1947-1949.; 6 leaves. Typescript and carbon. (Box 3, Folder 1)
          Included are 2 versions, plus printed copies of the articles (5 copies). The article was published in the This Week Magazine section Words to Live By, of the Los Angeles Times, November 27, 1949.
          With this is a letter to Kenneth Macgowan from the acting editor of This Week Magazine, New York, October 14, 1949 (1 leaf. Typescript).
        - [Commentaries on a film by Eisenstein of anthropological sites in Mexico and Yucatan] n.p., 14 leaves. Typescript and carbon. (Box 3, Folder 1)
          Included are 2 commentaries.
        - Review of The Ancient Maya by Sylvanus Griswold Morley, and An Album of Maya Architecture by Tatiana Oriskouriokoff. New York, January 1947.; 10 leaves. Typescript (carbon). 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 1)
          Included is a printed copy of the review, clipped from the New York Herald Tribune Weekly Book Review, January 26, 1947.
        - Review entitled The rediscovery of America, of the book Aztecs of Mexico, by George C. Vaillant. n.p., n.d.; 6 leaves. Typescript, with many corrections. (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Review of El Museo del Oro, introduction by Gregorio Mernandez de Alba. n.p., 1944.; 2 leaves. Typescript (carbon). 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Review of Treasure in the Dust, by Frank S. Hibben. Los Angeles, n.d.; 2 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - The calveras skull. Los Angeles (?), 1949.; 14 leaves. Typescript and carbon. (Box 3, Folder 2)
          Included are 2 versions; 2 copies of 1 version, and 3 copies of another, plus 2 extra leaves. Not known if published.
          With this is a letter from Mr. Macgowan's agent, Nannine Joseph re this article and the following article. New York, August 30, 1949 (1 leaf. Typescript).
        - John Lloyd Stephens. Los Angeles, 1949.; 21 leaves. Typescript and carbon. (Box 3, Folder 2)
          Included are 3 copies, and notes on cards. Not known if published.
        - The old stone age in America. n.p., n.d.; Approximately 200 leaves. Typescript (carbon). Not known if published. (Box 3, Folder 3)
          This work might very well be an early version, or a preliminary work leading up to Mr. Macgowan's book Early Man in the New World.)
        - The orientation of middle American sites. Los Angeles, California, 1945.; 28 leaves. Typescript (some carbon) and several notes. (Box 3, Folder 4)
          Included here are 11 reprints of the article.
          This article was published in American Antiquity, vol.2 no.2, October 1945.
        - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re The orientation of middle American sites. v.p., v.d.; 8 items. Typescript and photocopy. (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Byers, Douglas S., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Marquina, Ignacio., 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Merrill, Robert H., 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Satterthwaite, Linton., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - Also included are 2 letters, 1 carbon of a letter from Kenneth Macgowan to Sylvanus G. Morley, no reply included, and 1 unidentified letter to Kenneth Macgowan. (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - Printed articles re anthropology, published in newspapers and periodicals. v.p., 1945-1948.; 3 items. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Late mastondontes in Ecudor. n.p., 1928-1930.; 43 leaves. Manuscript and typescript.
      - Miscellaneous material re anthropology books., Approximately 88 items. (Box 3, Folder 7)
        Including some correspondence, typed and notated booklists, orders and invoices.
      - Book catalogs, printed lists, and announcements re anthropology books. v.p., v.d.; 7 items. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Book catalogs referring primarily to works re anthropology. Lima, Peru, 1964.; 3 items. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Anthropology - Ephemera
      - Printed articles, brochures and pamphlets re the American Indian. v.p., 1928-1961.; 11 items. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Various publications re the American Indian. v.p., 1947-1962.; 5 items. (Box 4, Folder 2)
        Includes paperbound works by various authors.
      - Miscellaneous material re the Southwest Museum, a museum of American Indian study. [California], v.d.; 10 items. (Box 4, Folder 3)
        Includes various publications of the Southwest Museum.
      - Publications re anthropological studies in Guatemala. v.p., 1963.; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Publications re anthropological studies of Mexico. v.p., v.d.; 9 items. (Box 4, Folder 5)
        Includes mainly magazine articles, and some pamphlets.
      - Publications re anthropological studies of Mexico. Mexico, D.F., 1962, 1963.; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 6)
        Includes 2 issues of Revista Mexicana de Estudios Anthropologicos.
      - Publications re anthropological studies of Peru. v.p., v.d.; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 7)
        Includes a clipped article, magazine, and pamphlets.
      - Miscellaneous material re various aspects of anthropology. v.p., v.d.; 9 items. (Box 5, Folder 1)
        Includes clippings charts, pamphlets, photos, etc.
      - Miscellaneous material... continued. v.p., v.d.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous material... continued. v.p., v.d.; 7 items. (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous material... continued. v.p., v.d.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Anthropology, Archaeology, Ethnology: Books, Pamphlets, and Other Ephemera
      - Various publications concerning archaeological and ethnological studies. v.p., v.d.; 6 items. (Box 6, Folder 1)
        Includes reprints of the Bureau of American Ethnology, periodicals, reprints of articles, and archaeological survey reports.
        (Continued in next folder)
      - Various publications... continued. v.p., v.d.; 4 items. (Box 6, Folder 2)
        Includes 2 issues of a periodical, Katunob, plus map charts.
      - Smithsonian Institution. Bureau of American Ethnology. Bulletins, no.178, 186, 187, 189, and 190. Washington, D.C., 1963 and 1964.; 5 items. (Box 6)
        (Filed Without Folders)
        These Bulletins, individually bound, were written by different authors, and treat such subjects as the Huron Indians, the Iroquois, and other Indian studies, plus river basin surveys. One item consists of an index to Bulletins 1-100.
    - Anthropology - Manuscript Material, Illustrations, and Ephemera pertaining to Kenneth Macgowan's Book, Early Man In The New World
      - [Introduction]? to Early man in the new world. n.p., n.d.; 12 leaves. Typescript and carbon. 2 copies. (Box 7, Folder 1)
        This appears to be introductory material for the book.
      - --- Early man in the new world. n.p., n.d.; 186 leaves. Typescript (carbon), bound in brown cover. (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Apparently this is an early version of the work.
      - --- Early man in the new world. Galley proof sheets. The Macmillan Company, New York, 1950.; 65 sheets. This is an incomplete proof copy, primarily consisting of proofs of preliminary pages, and illustrations. Some of the sheets are annotated. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - --- Early man in the new world. [New York], January 21, 1950.; 89 sheets. Galley proofs, 1 set duplicate proof copy, with preliminary pages omitted, uncorrected. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - --- Early man in the new world; miscellaneous leaves of manuscript. n.p., 1950.; 44 leaves. Typescript (carbon). There is no particular order to the material, and the leaves have many corrections. (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - --- Early man in the new world; synopsis of the work, miscellaneous leaves of manuscript, and various notes. n.p., 22 leaves. Typescript (some carbon). (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - --- Article entitled The idea of regency of man in America, n.p., n.d.; 63 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Used in research for the writing of Early man in the new world, perhaps as a preliminary work for the text. No author is indicated, but this was probably written by Kenneth Macgowan.
      - Material used in research for Early man in the new world. n.p., n.d.; 26 items. (Box 7, Folder 8)
        Included are typescript notes, charts, ephemera, etc.
      - Untitled article about panpipes, n.p., n.d.; 14 leaves. Manuscript and typescript, including notes. (Box 7, Folder 9)
        Author not indicated, apparently used in research by Kenneth Macgowan for Early man in the new world.
      - Charts used to illustrate Early man in the new world. n.p., 1950.; 3 items. (Box 8, Folder 1)
        Included are 3 examples of the same chart, paste-up work.
      - Material used for illustrations for Early man in the new world. n.p., 1950.; Approximately 100 items. (Box 8, Folder 2)
        Included are paste-up sheets, photocopies of drawings, etc.
      - Negatives of photographs of illustrations for Early man in the new world. n.p., 1950.; Approximately 45 negatives. (Box 8, Folder 3)
        Most of the items are filed in separate envelopes, a few with positive prints.
      - Photographs and photocopies of various drawings and charts, compiled for selection and possible use as illustrations for Early man in the new world. n.p., 1950.; 80 items. Various sizes. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Additional photographs, many used in research, and some no doubt were used as illustrations for Early man in the new world. n.p., 89 items. Various sizes. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Printed proof copies of illustrations and jacket design for Early man in the new world. [New York?], 1950.; 34 items. Also included are a few cut-outs, probably used for illustrations. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Reviews and notices re Early man in the new world, clipped from newspapers and periodicals. v.p., January-July 1950.; 90 items. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Reviews and notices re Early man in the new world.... continued. v.p., August 1950-1951.; 70 items. (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Copies of reviews and excerpts of reviews by various authors for Early man in the new world. v.p., 1950.; 11 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Anthropology - Correspondence Pertaining to Kenneth Macgowan's Book, Early Man In The New World
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re Early man in the new world. v.p., 1945-1961.; 75 items. Holograph and typescript (some carbon). Arranged alphabetically, A - D. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Anderson, Edgar., 2 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Antevs, Ernst., 16 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Apling, Harry., 2 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Arellano, A.R.V., 2 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Arndt, Armin W., 1 item. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Behre, E.A., 1 item. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Black, Glenn A., 1 item. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Bryan, Kirk., 3 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Canada. Universities. University of Toronto press., 2 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Carter, George F., 5 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Champe, John L., 1 item. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Chicago Natural History Museum., 3 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Colbert, Edwin H., 1 item. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Commins, Saxe., 5 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Cressman, L.S., 1 item. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Daly, Reginald A., 3 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Deuel, Thorne., 1 item. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Dick, Herbert W., 1 item. (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Doubleday and Company, Incorporated, publishers., 14 items. (Box 9, Folder 1)